AMY GOODMAN: We’re on the road in San Diego,
California.
President Trump is facing yet another major
scandal.
The New York Times is reporting Trump personally
asked FBI Director James Comey to end the
agency’s investigation into Trump’s former
national security adviser, Michael Flynn.
On Tuesday night, Republican Senator John
McCain said the Trump scandals are reaching
"Watergate size and scale."
SEN. JOHN McCAIN: I think we’ve seen this movie
before.
I think it’s reaching the point where it’s
of Watergate size and scale and a couple of
other scandals that you and I have seen.
It’s the centipede that the shoe continues
to drop.
And every couple of days, there’s a new
aspect of this really unhappy situation.
AMY GOODMAN: Speaking from the Senate floor,
New York Democrat, Senate Minority Leader
Chuck Schumer told his colleagues, "History
is watching."
SEN. CHUCK SCHUMER: In a week full of revelation
after revelation, on a day when we thought
things couldn’t get any worse, they have.
I was shaken by the report in The New York
Times that alleged that the president tried
to shut down an active FBI investigation into
a close political associate.
And we are only one day removed from stunning
allegations that the president may have divulged
classified information to a known adversary.
Concerns about our national security, the
rule of law, the independence of our nation’s
highest law enforcement agencies are mounting.
The country is being tested in unprecedented
ways.
I say to all of my colleagues in the Senate:
History is watching.
AMY GOODMAN: The New York Times reports President
Trump made the extraordinary request to James
Comey during an Oval Office meeting on February
14th—one day after Trump fired Flynn for
lying publicly and privately about his contacts
with Russian officials.
Trump reportedly asked Vice President Mike
Pence and Attorney General Jeff Sessions to
leave the room before asking Comey to drop
the investigation into the—into Mike Flynn.
After the meeting, Comey wrote a memo quoting
the president saying, "I hope you can see
your way clear to letting this go, to letting
Flynn go.
He is a good guy.
I hope you can let this go."
In addition, President Trump reportedly urged
Comey to consider jailing reporters for publishing
classified information.
Trump fired Comey last week, days after he
requested more resources for the FBI’s probe
into Russian meddling in the 2016 election.
On Tuesday night, Republican Congressman Jason
Chaffetz, chair of the House Oversight Committee,
called on the FBI turn over all "memoranda,
notes, summaries, and recordings" of discussions
between Trump and Comey.
The New York Times report came just a day
after The Washington Post revealed President
Trump had disclosed highly classified intelligence
to Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov
and Russian Ambassador Sergey Kislyak at the
White House.
We’re joined now by John Kiriakou, who spent
14 years at the CIA as an analyst and case
officer.
In 2007, he became the first CIA official
to publicly confirm the Bush administration’s
use of waterboarding.
In January 2013, Kiriakou was sentenced to
two-and-a-half years in prison after pleading
guilty to confirming the identity of a covert
officer to a reporter, who actually did not
publish it.
Kiriakou’s memoir, which has just been published,
is titled Doing Time Like a Spy: How the CIA
Taught Me to Survive and Thrive in Prison.
John Kiriakou, welcome to Democracy Now!
JOHN KIRIAKOU: Thank you so much.
AMY GOODMAN: Thanks so much for joining us.
Can you respond to this latest scandal at
the White House?
JOHN KIRIAKOU: I’m very, very, even gravely,
concerned about the path that this scandal
seems to be taking.
It’s more like an onion than it is one single
scandal.
Every time we peel one layer off the onion,
there’s another scandal underneath it.
And now we have members of Congress talking
about impeachment.
I think impeachment, frankly, is something
that is a real possibility, something we ought
to be discussing.
I think that it’s—it’s pretty clear
that the president has committed obstruction
of justice.
And let’s face it.
Director Comey is a player in Washington.
He’s been around the block.
Do we really think that he released the most
explosive memo he has, knowing that he wrote
memos every time he spoke with President Trump?
My guess is, there’s a lot more explosive
information out there waiting to be released.
AMY GOODMAN: Well, can you talk about exactly
the significance of what Comey’s memo reveals
that Trump asked him to do on February 14th
in a meeting where, according to The New York
Times, he told Jeff Sessions and, I think
it was, the vice president to step out of
the room and then asked Comey to drop the
investigation into his, well, fired national
security adviser, Mike Flynn?
He had fired him the day before.
JOHN KIRIAKOU: That he asked the vice president
to leave the room, to me, is damning information.
That tells me that the president knew exactly
what he was doing, that he knew that he was
going to have to say something that was inappropriate
and perhaps illegal, and he likely wanted
no other witnesses.
That way, whatever Director Comey eventually
came out to say, the president could say he’s
a liar.
Well, I think he overplayed his hand.
He intimated last week that there were tapes
of that conversation.
I think that the Congress should act immediately
to subpoena those tapes, if they exist.
My guess is they’re going to confirm Director
Comey’s version of that conversation.
AMY GOODMAN: And, of course, now Congress
is calling on Comey to testify, which apparently
he is willing to do.
The significance of what this fired FBI director
could say in one of these hearings?
JOHN KIRIAKOU: Well, it was fascinating to
me, Amy, that Director Comey declined to testify
in a closed session of the Senate Intelligence
Committee but said that he was willing to
testify in an open session.
That’s potentially explosive.
I think what many congressmen and senators
on Capitol Hill expect is that Director Comey
is going to reveal the possibility that other
crimes were committed, either by the president
or by those around him.
AMY GOODMAN: And also, the significance of
the allegation that President Trump revealed
highly classified information to the Russian
officials—the foreign minister, Lavrov,
and the Russian ambassador, Kislyak?
I mean, this is not illegal.
The president—
JOHN KIRIAKOU: Right.
AMY GOODMAN: —can do what he wants to in
this regard.
Is that right?
JOHN KIRIAKOU: That’s right.
The president has final declassification authority
over all information controlled by the federal
government.
So, if he leaks classified information—and
apparently he did—it’s not—it’s technically
not a crime.
It was certainly inappropriate.
And if you’re going to leak classified information,
my god, the last country you want to leak
it to is the Russians.
But this goes a little bit deeper.
I think this just shows how impetuous this
president is and how he frequently acts from
his gut.
He flies off the handle.
He does things without thinking them through.
And to me, it just sort of makes it difficult
to figure out how he can get through a 4-year
term going down this path.
This is—this is one problem, one scandal
after the other, and it’s cumulative.
It takes a toll.